Van den Haag, Ernest; Papers apap135
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ernest Van Den Haag Papers
1935-2000
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Van den Haag, Ernest
apap135
11.45 cubic ft. 1 audiotape
This collection is predominantly composed of Ernest van den Haag’s publications from 1950-2000, including articles in published form, drafts, and related correspondence.
Biographical Sketch
Ernest van den Haag (1914-2002) was a conservative commentator of social issues, especially crime, and one of America's foremost proponents of the death penalty [Pace, Eric. "Ernest van den Haag, Educator and Backer of the Death Penalty". New York Times, 27 March 2002, sec. A:21].
He said he was born an intellectual and called himself a strong political conservative, but almost a libertarian. He authored several books and book chapters and contributed hundreds of articles to journals, magazines, and newspapers from 1950-2000.
Ernest van den Haag was born in The Hague in 1914 and was raised in Italy where he began his early political life as a left-wing activist and communist. In 1937 he was nearly killed by a political assassin from Mussolini's fascist regime. Van den Haag suffered five bullet wounds and spent nearly three years in Italian prisons, including 18 months in solitary confinement in Naples before the start of World War II. After being released and fearing re-imprisonment, he fled to Switzerland and then to France where he studied psychiatry at the Sorbonne in Paris. Soon, he was arrested as an enemy alien Italian and an agitator against the government. He managed to escape to Spain and then to Portugal prior to Hitler's invasion. From Portugal he was able to make his way to the United States in 1940 where he arrived not knowing English. In New York he sold vegetables and worked as a bus boy. He was able to secure admission to the University of Iowa where a group of faculty recognized his intellectual gifts and agreed to pay his tuition.
After receiving his M.A. in economics in 1942 as the U.S. entered World War II, van den Haag went to work for the Office of War Information as a propaganda analyst. That same year he met Sidney Hook, a famous social philosopher, who was a catalyst in van den Haag's thinking. Of his friendship with Sydney Hook, van den Haag said, "Sydney converted me and I not only stopped being a communist but I became an anti-communist although it no longer means much" [Machan, Tibor. The Intellectual Portrait Series: A Conversation with Ernest van den Haag. Indianapolis: Liberty Fund, 2000]. He began a part-time teaching career as an instructor at Hofstra College of New York lecturing in Psychology and Sociology. He received his Ph.D. in Economics from New York University in 1952. As early as 1953, van den Haag was contributing essays to magazines arguing against communism. In 1956, van den Haag authored his first book,Education as an Industry and co-authored a sociology textbook, The Fabric of Society, in 1957.
Ernest van den Haag's writings garnered the attention of William F. Buckley, Jr. when, in 1957, Buckley asked him to contribute articles to the National Review. From 1957 to 1994, van den Haag wrote close to 200 articles for the National Review and remained a friend and consultant for 45 years. Buckley's obituary of van den Haag stated: "His special skill was the crisp essay in which he distilled his thought and analysis with precisionist care" [Buckley, Jr., William F. Ernest van den Haag, R.I.P. (Obituary).National Review, 22 April 2002].
Van den Haag's book, Punishing Criminals: Concerning a Very Old and Painful Question (Basic Books, 1975), had a long popularity and launched his status as an expert and fearless debater in issues of criminal justice and the death penalty. In addition to his writing career, van den Haag was an expert witness for many court cases in local, state, federal, and international jurisdictions. He testified as an expert in areas including desegregation, criminal justice, and pornography. He was comfortable taking controversial stands on tough issues such as his criticism over Brown v. Board of Education. He was also a fierce debater of many issues. "He has said he would debate anyone on anything. He has read and thought lucidly about everything", said Edward Banfield, professor of Government at Harvard University [Feulner, Jr., Edwin J. "A Note on Ernest van den Haag". In Smashing Liberal Icons: A Collection of Debates. Washington, D.C.: Heritage Foundation, 1984]. Van den Haag was especially active in debating the issue of the death penalty. He spent most of his life defending the issue based on the argument of deterrence, but later evolved the basis of his argument on the need for the death penalty as just punishment for severe criminals.
Ernest van den Haag accomplished much in his lifetime. Among the many positions he held were: Lecturer in Psychology and Sociology, The New School for Social Research, 1953-1980; Adjunct Professor, New York University; Psychoanalyst in private practice, 1955-1982; Fellow of the American Sociological Association beginning in 1959; 1966 Guggenheim Fellow; 1972 Senior Fellow for the National Endowment for the Humanities; Visiting Professor, CUNY; Lecturer at dozens of universities and colleges including Harvard, Yale, Cornell, and Berkeley; Visiting Professor of Criminology, School of Criminal Justice, State University of New York at Albany, 1978-1983; John M. Olin Professor of Jurisprudence and Public Policy, Fordham University, 1982-1988; Distinguished Scholar, The Heritage Foundation; Member, Council on Foreign Relations; Philadelphia Society (Former President 1978-1979).
Ernest van den Haag spoke at conferences as recently as 1999 and published articles through 2000. Van den Haag died after a brief illness at age 88 on March 21, 2002, in Mendham, NJ.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Ernest van den Haag cover the years 1935-2000. His publications from 1950-2000 comprise the bulk of the collection. Comparing this collection of publications to his curriculum vitae, it appears that most of his published and unpublished materials are contained in the collection. Van den Haag took special care to organize his writings by assigning them a number, probably in order of creation, placing each publication, along with rough drafts and related correspondence, into individual folders. He often followed up on references to his work, adding them to the appropriate folder. The publications in this collection include articles in published form, drafts, and related correspondence. Types of publications include transcripts from appearances on television shows in the 1970s and 1980s, files on the books which he authored, rough drafts for chapters, and hundreds of articles written for various journals, magazines, and newspapers from 1950-2000. A few articles include printed versions in at least five other languages.
The collection's publications cover a wide array of social science issues of the mid to late 20th century from an intellectual conservative's view. Topics include American culture, criminal justice, education, conservatism versus liberalism, and American politics. Van den Haag had a special political interest in U.S. foreign policy and commented on the Vietnam War, foreign wars, and the issues of the Cold War. His writing had an impact on people and events of his day. President Nixon once wrote van den Haag to thank him for the balanced views concerning the U.S. soldiers and war crimes during Vietnam when he offered during his appearance on the Dick Cavett Show. Congressman Charles Rangel wrote to express his opposing views to van den Haag on the legalization of drugs. Sometimes van den Haag's articles would spark a debate between himself and other authors that would continue over the course of several issues of a periodical.
The collection contains some court testimony from van den Haag as an expert witness in cases including the U.S. House and Senate hearings and U.S. Supreme Court cases concerning desegregation in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Also represented are pornography cases between towns and theaters both at the local and U.S. Supreme Court levels.
The collection contains many articles, debate notes, and drafts of speeches from conferences and meetings discussing capital punishment. Most of these cover the period from the mid-1980s to the early 1990s.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Mary Beth O'Connor, executor of the estate of Ernest van den Haag, in May 2002.
Related Materials
A book collection was given to the University Libraries along with the manuscript collection and is part of the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives' book collection.
Related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found at the National Death Penalty Archive and subject pages for Criminal Justice and Prisons, Education, Military and Armed Conflict, and Public Servants and Politicians.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Africana Studies; Public Servants; Political Science; Military and Armed Conflict; Education; Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Labor--United States.; Unemployment--United States.; Political science--Philosophy.; Capital punishment.; Capital punishment--Law and legislation--United States--History.; School integration.; Social science literature.; Psychology and philosophy.; Pornography--Law and legislation--United States--Cases.; Drugs--Law and legislation--United States--Legislative history.; Sex instruction.; Vietnam Conflict, 1961-1975.; United States--Economic conditions.; Publications (document genre); Periodicals; Lecture notes; Clippings; Correspondence; Legal documents; Van den Haag, Ernest
- Biographical, 1950-1998; 1; 0.17 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains two large bibliographies of Ernest van den Haag's writings. The first bibliography covers his works from 1950-1982. The second includes his writings up to 1998. These bibliographies organize his writings alphabetically by topic and each publication includes an assigned number. These numbers do not reflect a strict, but rather general chronological order (i.e. number one was published in 1968 while number two was published in 1954). The numbering system probably reflects the order in which the articles were begun. Some were published quickly while others took longer. This series also contains van den Haag's curriculum vitae from 1973-1998 as well as short biographies from 1973-1989.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bibliography, 1950-1982 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 1)
  - Bibliography, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1973-1998 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 3)
  - Short Biographies, 1973-1989 (Box 1 (1-Biographical), Folder 4)
- Publications, 1949-2000; 2; 7.49 cubic ft.
  - Numbered, 1950-2000; 2.1; 6.17 cubic ft.
    This subseries contains the published writings of Ernest van den Haag arranged numerically by the number assigned each. This subseries represents the bulk of the collection and is one of the best sources for studying the philosophy of Ernest van den Haag. He wrote articles that cover a wide spectrum of political and social issues of his day. This subseries is unique in that it contains not only van den Haag's drafts, but in most cases the articles in their final published form, providing the researcher a glimpse of the contemporary context. These publications include drafts for books, reviews, chapters, and articles by van den Haag. The publications were assigned individual numbers probably reflecting the order of creation not the date of publication. The arrangement within each folder is as follows: the final published form of the article usually containing the periodical cover page, the contents page, and the article itself; correspondence, usually between van den Haag and the publisher, as well as any other related correspondence; rough drafts of the article, usually in order from oldest to newest; research material used in creation of the article as well as articles from other authors that represent debate over van den Haag's views and facts. Publication number 194 contains a letter from President Nixon thanking van den Haag for his balanced views on war crimes in Vietnam. Publication number 338 is an excellent example of the type of controversy surrounding some articles written by van den Haag. Publication number 439 contains a letter from Congressman Charles Rangel opposing Haag's views on the legalization of illegal drugs.
    Note: Number assigned by the creator in the bibliography found in Series 1.
    Arranged numerically.
    - 1. "Academic Freedom in the United States", Law and Contemporary Problems: Academic Freedom, School of Law, Duke University, 1963 Summer (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 1)
    - 1a. "Academic Freedom and its Defense", Report of the Eighteenth Educational Conference, and Phi Delta Kappan, 1953; 1954 December (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 2)
    - 1c. "The Communist Teacher Can't Be Free", The New Leader, 1953 May 25 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 3)
    - 1d. "Student Loyalty: Should It Be Questioned", The New Leader, 1960 February 01 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 4)
    - 2. "Creativity, Health and Art", Arts and Sciences, Spring 1963, and the Journal of Psychoanalysis (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 5)
    - 2b. "Abstraction vs. Conscience In Art: A Symposium", Ameryka (Slavik), Translation from American Illustrated, no. 70 and no. 98, 1963 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 6)
    - 3. Review of "American Higher Education in the 1960's" by Robert J. Havinghurst, American Journal of Sociology, 1961 May (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 7)
    - 4. Review of "German Catholics in Hitler's War" by Gordan Zahn, American Sociological Review, 1958 June (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 8)
    - 5. Review of "America as a Civilization" by Max Lerner, American Sociological Review, June 1958, and Encounter, 1958 August (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 9)
    - 6. Review of "Social Control in a Free Society" by Loren C. Eiseley, et al, American Sociological Review, 1958 June (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 10)
    - 7. Review of "Responsibility in Mass Communication" by Wilbur Schram, American Sociological Review, 1968 October (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 11)
    - 8. Reviews of Books - Containing Articles by van Den Haag, 1957-1967 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 12)
    - 9. Review of "Freud and the Twentieth Century", ed. by Benjamin Nelson, American Sociological Review, 1960 February (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 13)
    - 10. "Comment on Books of the Past Ten Years", American Scholar, 1965 Summer (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 14)
    - 11. "Reflection on Mass Culture", American Scholar, 1960 Spring (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 15)
    - 12a. "La Cultura Di Mass Manufatto Dell Industria", Mercurio, 1959 April (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 16)
    - 12b. "Sur la Culture Populaire Americaine", Les Temps Modernes, November 1958, and Avanti, November 1958 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 17)
    - 12c. Kutura Masowa", Dokumenty, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 18)
    - 12d. "Notes on Mass Culture in America", Tempo Presente (Rome), November 1957, Diagenes (English and French) 1957, Tempo Presente, 1960 March (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 19)
    - 12i. "Symposium on TV", Dissent, 1960 Summer (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 20)
    - 12j. "Menance of Mass Media", The New Leader, 1957 July 29 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 21)
    - 12k. Letter to the Editor on Professor Shils' Comment on Mass Culture, Swanee Review, 1958 Spring; 1958 Fall (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 22)
    - 13. "Creating Cities for Human Beings, "American Scholar, 1959 Fall (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 23)
    - 13a. "Creating Cities for Human Beings", Communita, 1959 December (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 24)
    - 13c. "Creating Cities for Human Beings", in The Troubled Metropolis, Ernest van den Haag Rand Institute on Public Affairs, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 25)
    - 13d. "Salviamo Le Citta", Mercurio, 1960 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 26)
    - 13e. "Notes on New York Housing", Dissent, 1961 Summer (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 27)
    - 13f. "Building In Limbo", Columbia Univ. School of Architecture, 1961 Spring (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 28)
    - 14. Review of "Masters of Deceit", by J. Edgar Hoover, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1958 September (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 29)
    - 15. Review of "Roots of American Communism" by Theodore Draper, Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1957 September (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 30)
    - 16. "Controlling Subversive Groups", Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1955 July (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 31)
    - 17. "Higher Education on the Cuff", Fortune, 1952 May (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 32)
    - 17a. "Should College Be Restricted to the Intellectual Elite?" New York Post, Undated (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 33)
    - 18. "Snobbery", The British Journal of Sociology, 1956 September (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 34)
    - 19. "What to Do About Advertising", in Exploring Advertising, 1962-1970 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 35)
      Edited by Otto Keppner, 1970, Brewers Digest, June 1962, and Commentary, May 1962
    - 20. "Madison Avenue Witchcraft", Review of "Battle for the Mind" and "The Hidden Pervaders", American Sociology Review, 1958 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 36)
    - 21. "McCarthyism and the Professors", Review of "The Academic Mind" by Paul Lazarsfeld, Commentary, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 37)
    - 22. "Affluence, Galbraith, The Democrats", Commentary, 1960 September (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 38)
    - 23. "Affluence", E.v.d.Haag's Reply to Lewis Coser, Commentary, 1961 January (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 39)
    - 24. "Federal Aid to Parochial Schools, Commentary, 1961 July (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 40)
    - 25. "More Immigration?" National Review, 1965 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 41)
    - 25a. Reply to J. Hirschleifer on "More Immigration?", National Review, 1965 November 02 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 42)
    - 26. "On Mobilization for Youth", Letter to the Editor on Bierstedts' attack on "Mobilization for youth, American Sociological Review, 1965 August (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 43)
    - 28. "Automated Man?" Manipulators of Human Destiny, Fall Lecture Series, Central Connecticut State College, 1966 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 44)
    - 31. "Quota Ineptum", (On Censorship), Ethics, 1972 July (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 45)
    - 32. "Love or Marriage", Harpers, 1962 May (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 46)
    - 32a. "Love: Is this day the Beginning of the End?" Nova, 1965 June (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 47)
    - 33. "The Planners and the Planned, "Modern Age, 1964 Spring (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 48)
    - 34. "Private and Public Expenditures", Modern Age, Spring 1962 and Christian Economics, 1963 March 05 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 49)
    - 35. "The Soul Recovers Radical Innocence", Modern Age, 1959 Summer (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 50)
    - 35a. "The Sensibility of Marrel Ayme", The New Leader, 1959 August 03-1959 August 10 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 51)
    - 36. "Make Tax Honesty Rewarding: A Proposal", Modern Age, 1958 Winter (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 52)
    - 37. "Jack Kerouac and the Beat Generation", Los Temps Modernes, 1959 September (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 53)
    - 37a. "Glie Eroi Di Kerovac", (The Heroes of Kerovac), Tempo Presente, 1958 November (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 54)
    - 38. "Learning How to Learn, "Review of "Memo to a College Trustee" By Beardsley Ruml, The Reporter, 1959 August 30 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 55)
    - 39. "Not Seven, Not Lively, Not Arts", National Review, 1958 January 11 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 56)
    - 40. "Communism, Democracy and Religion", National Review, 1958 March 22 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 57)
    - 41. "Studded with Quotations", Review of "The Capitalist Manifesto" by Louis O. Kelso, National Review, 1958 October 25 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 58)
    - 42. Review of "Plain Talk from Campus" by John Perkins, National Review, 1959 August 15 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 59)
    - 43. "Must Conservatives Repudiate Keynes?" National Review, 1960 June 04 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 60)
    - 44. "Loss of Urbanity", Review of "The Death and Life of Great American Cities" by Jane Jacobs, National Review, 1961 December 30 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 61)
    - 45. "War in Katanga: Report of a Mission", National Review, March 27, 1962, and The American Committee for Aid to Katanga Freedom Fighters (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 62)
    - 46. "Crimes Against Humanity", Review of "Eichmann in Jerusalem" by Hannah Arendt, National Review, 1963 August 27 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 63)
    - 47. "The Lessons of the Congo", National Review, 1964 September 08 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 64)
    - 49. "The U.N.'s Idiot Policy in Katanga", National Review, 1965 January 26 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 65)
    - 50. Review of "The Wolfenden Report", Behavioral Science Book Service, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 66)
    - 51. "Male Self - Hatred", Review of "The National Superiority of Women" by Ashley Montagu, The New Leader, 1963 July 06 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 67)
    - 53. "Some Sociology of Value", Review of "Social Theory" by Lewis Coser, The New Leader, 1958 July 07 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 68)
    - 55. "A Modest Farm Proposal", The New Leader, 1961 February 27 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 69)
    - 56. "Neither Adult Nor Education", Review of "University Adult Education" by Renee and William Peterson, The New Leader, 1961 November 27 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 70)
    - 57. "Either/Or: Religion and Communism: An Open Letter to Sidney Hook", Partisan Review, 1950 July-1950 August (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 71)
    - 59. "Egalitarisme Aux U.S.A.", Preuves, 1954 January (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 72)
    - 61. "Unemployment in Planned and Capitalistic Economies", Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1954 February (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 73)
    - 61a. Reply to Mr. Holzman's Comments on "Unemployment in Planned and Capitalistic Economies", Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1955 August (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 74)
    - 62. "Psychoanalysis and Utopia", Freud Memorial Lecture, and Bulletin of the Philadelphia Association for Psychoanalysis, 1964 May 22; 1965 June (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 75)
    - 62a. "The New Utopians and the New Left", Address Delivered at the American Political Science Association, 1969 September 02 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 76)
    - 63. "Demographers Go to the New World", Review of "The Family and Population Control", by Reuben Hill, et al., Saturday Review, 1959 June 30 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 77)
    - 64. "Man As An Object of Science", Science, 1959 January 30 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 78)
    - 65. "For A Peace Conference in Yugoslavia", The New Leader, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 79)
    - 66. Reply to "Conformity Revisited" by Everett Wilson, Trans - Action, 1964 November-1964 December (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 80)
    - 67. Review of "How Now Kate" Edited by Elaine Showalter, National Review, 1970 September 22 (Box 1 (2-Publications), Folder 81)